Division of Nutritional Sciences Cooperative Extension Nutrition Program Records, 1940-2005.
Division of Nutritional Sciences Cooperative Extension Nutrition Program Records
- Title
  - Inventory for Youth Programming, 1970-1979 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Overview Of Efforts For The Youth In The 70s By Martha C. Mapes (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Organizational and Program Directions for NY 4-H Programs (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Goals for 4-H in the 70s: A Progress Report
    - 4-H in Century III: program Directions in 4-H, 1976-1986
    - Early Mapes Correspondence
  - Section A: First Efforts to Better Reach Disadvantaged Youth
  - Youth focused Inservices for all agents, 1971,1972 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Youth Nutrition: Are You With It?
    - Youth Nutrition: Facing New Challenges
  - Try Something New.. MMM Good: EFNEP youth project to broaden food acceptability (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Evaluation Efforts: Try Something New (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Evaluation Model
    - Evaluation By Agents
    - Evaluation In Albany And Rensselaer Counties
    - Evaluation In Cortland County
  - Food Combos: EFNEP youth project (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - InDepth Training for agents: process Evaluation of a Nutrition Education Program in a Field Setting, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Section B: New and Revised 4-H food and Nutrition Projects
  - 4-H Ad Hoc Agent Advisory Committee Recommendations (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - 4-H Food In The Morning (Replacement For Breakfast Is Ready) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - 4-H Food Preservation (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - 4-H Snack Wisely (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - 4-H A Garden Of Snacks (NYC Gardening) (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Snack Resource Packet For Agents (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - 4-H The Versatile Vegetable (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - 4-H Supplementary Resource: Useful Facts About Baking (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - 4-H Self Determined Project (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Section C: Special youth pilots
  - GULP Pilot and Evaluation: Newsprint magazine to appeal hard to reach youth, 1977-01-1977-03 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - FAD Dieting Portfolio - 6 lesson project on body image etc (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Perspective on Anorexia Nervosa (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Grahan Kerr pilots: "Light and Easy" and "Switched on Kitchen", Johnson City School Lunch, Photos and Slides (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Food Waste/Trash Tells A Tale (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Section D: Youth Projects designed for the classroom
  - Learning Nutrition Through Discovery plus revision (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Iron and Energy Our Food And Our Needs slide sets (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Yardsticks For Nutrition (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Buy And Buy (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Section E: Nutrition Education for Parents
  - How Children Learn About Food (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Nutrition In Action For The Child (Slide Set) (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Children's Behavior Responses To TV Food Advertisements, JNE Article, 1974-09 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Box 5: K-12 Nutrition Strand, K-6 Nutrition Comes Alive 1969-1982
  - Inventory: Phase I and II Curriculum Development (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Nutrition Curriculum Development by Dept. of Human Nutrition and Food and Division of Nutritional Sciences with New york State Dept. of Education, 1969,1978 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Section A: 1967-1971 Phase I Curriculum Development
  - Publishes articles in support of health education Sliepcevich, E.,Sinacore,J.,Speno,E.,Harrison,G.(SHES National Study and NY Initiatives) (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "Nutrition Education As Part Of Health Education", Presentation By Gail Harrison, Cornell U., Note discussion of NY State Law 787, 1967-05 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Cornell Contract With College Of Human Ecology: Developmet Of NY Nutrition Starnd K-12 Curriculum, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Inservice For Extension Field Staff "Nutirion in Health Education", 1970 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Sample of K-3 and 7-9 Nutrition Starnd of Curriculum
    - Overview of teaching units, basic health framework, and fundamental nutrition concepts
  - Hearings: "School Nutrition Education Programs", McGovern Committee (Senate Select Committee on Nutrition and Human Needs), 1973 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Section B: 1977-1978 Preliminary investigation: NY Consumer Health Education Contract With Cornell
  - Assembly bills and Cornell Ad Hoc Advisory Committee (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Section C: Phase II: 1978-1982 Nutrition Education Training Grant (NET)
  - Authorization bills, Ad Hoc Advisory Committee: Recommendations for nneds assessment and state plan, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - NET State Advisory Committee: Appointment, Correspondence And Minutes (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - New York State Plan For NET, Agent Reaction, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - New York City Nutrition Committee Challenge (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Five NET proposals and budget by Cornell Extension (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - NET-Cornell Budgets, Sub-Contracts, Costs, Minigrants, Copyright issues, Hubbard Contract Option, SlimLine Production (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Training of Regional NET Coordinators, Conference With BOCES Supervisors, Dean, Extension Administration (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Training Manual for NET Coordinators, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Developing a Tool for regional needs assessment by NET Coordinators: Approaches and Outcomes (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - NET Evaluation Contract: One school district upstate, Regional Evlauation NCA by MADISON, ONEIDA BOCES (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Early Childhood Nutrition Program (Pre - K) (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - PSA Series: Nineteen 30 second TV spots for 2-NET Contracts (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Sample Script, progress Report, Press Release, Tape of the Magic Cupboard (1/2 inch VHS Video)
  - Nutrition Comes Alive: K-6 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Promotional slide set and script
    - Presentation To SNE in Montreal, 1980
    - Initial Progress Report K-6, 1979
  - NET Evaluation of NCA K-6 by Ed Frongillo and teachers (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - 56th Annual report of NY State College of Human Ecology, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    Tow page coverage NCA with photos
  - Nutrition Comes Alive: Newspaper articles, photos in MVR Studio of production PSA's, State Fair activity (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - NET Newsletters, 1978-1980 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Section D: 1982 NY State Hunger Watch Task Force appointed by Gov. Carey
  - Nutrition Watch Documents (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Briefing Book, 1982-04
    - At-Risk Populations, 1984
    - Recommendations of the Nutrition Watch Committee
    - Committee Membership
  - Hearing Testimony By Martha Mapes, "The Responsibility of Government: Historical Perspective on Nutrition Education", 1982-04 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Section E: NET Publishes Curriculum
  - Early Childhood Nutrition Education - boxed program (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Nutrition Comes Alive - eight box program, Sample: Level 2 Be A Choosy Chewer (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Box 6:Nutrition Comes Alive Samples of K,1,3 in 1982
  - Three Grade Levels of Nutrition Comes Alive K-6 curriculum developed by Extension Faculty in the Division of Nutritional Sciences under the NET contract with the New York State Dept. of Education, 1978-1982 (Box 6)
    - Level K: Munch With Munch
    - Level 1: Lets Go Exploring
    - Level 3: The Food Peddlers
  - Box 7: Nutrition Comes Alive Samples of 4,5,6 in 1982
  - Three Grade Levels of the Original Nutrition Comes Alive K-6 curriculum developed by Extension Faculty in the Division of Nutritional Sciences under the NET contract with the New York State Dept. of Education, 1978-1982 (Box 7)
    - Level 4: On The Move
    - Level 5: The Nutrient Connection
    - Level 6: A Case Of Waste
  - Box 8: Revised Nutrition Comes Alive, Nutrition for Life 1985-1988
  - Inventory (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Overview: Phase III K-12 Curriculum Development, 1985-1988 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Section A: Documents supporting the DNS-NY State Dept. of Health Contract for Nutrition Comes Alive (NCA) K-6 revised
  - Proposal: Nutrition for Young New Yorkers: training and Support of Teachers (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Includes exchange between Mapes, Ramirez, Axelrod regarding jurisdiction
  - Process Objectives for NCA and Specific Revisions in NCA, 1979,1980,1985 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - In-Services for NCA K-3 Revised: Campus and Regional (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - NET Training Conference at Teachers College of Columbia Univ., 1986-04 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Teleconference from Rochester, New York, 1986-05 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Report of County Activity using NCA K-6 Teaching Packets, 1986-12 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Includes Newspaper Articles
  - NCA Cooperative Dissemination Plan between Cornell and State Education Dept (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - NCA Promo Slide Show (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Letters to agents and teachers (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Photos, Press Releases, Newspaper articles (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - NCA Newsletters, 1985-1986 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Section B: Documents supporting the DNS NY State Dept. of Health Contract for Nutrition for Life 7-12
  - Contracts and Correspondence for NFL 7-12 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - NFL Evaluation (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Cornell Press Releases, Newspaper Articles, Promotional leaflets, Photos (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Total K-12
    - Smart Start, Now You're Cooking, Fit Is It
    - Nutrition For Life: 7-8
    - Nutrition For Life: 9-12
  - Awards (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - AHEA Impact 2000 Recognition for Nutrition For Life
    - FDA National Consumer Education Materials Top 10 For ALIVE! Food and Fitness Magazine
  - Section C: Copies of Published 1985-1988 K-12 Curriculum developed by Cornell DNS Extension for NY State Dept. of Nutrition
  - Revised Nutrition Comes Alive packets Containing Teachers Guide and Student Work Book (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Level K Munch with Munch
    - Level 1 Lets Go Exploring
    - Level 2 Be A Choosy Chewer
    - Level 3 The Food Peddlers
    - Level 4 The Great Balancing Act
    - Level 5 The Nutrient Connection
    - Level 6 A Case of Waste
  - Nutrition For Life 7-8, A Notebook containing audio cassette, tapes, aposter, teacher guides and student activity sheets (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Spanning The Years
    - Exploring Food Choices
    - Food and Fitness
  - Nutrition For Life 9-12 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Fit Is It
    - A Smart Start
    - Now You're Cooking
  - ALIVE: Food and Fitness (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Magazine for teens including following topics:
      - Secrets of the Super Athlete
      - Eating and you Emotions
      - Making It On Your Own Recipes, Exercises, Health Trends
  - NYC Teenage Health Teaching Module (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Adaptation of Nutrition For Life, Grades 7-8 by Ruth Lowenberg under contract with Board of education, NYC using milk money refund per Court Order.
  - Box 9: In Process Archives for Extension Efforts for Youth
  - Inventory, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - DNS 4-H Youth Programming, 1992
      (Collected By Martha C. Mapes for Patricia Thonney and Tracy Farrell)
  - Section A: DNS Recommended Nutrition Resources
  - Information sheet for CCE Educators: 4-H Youth Development and Other Programming (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - 4-H Youth Development Nutrition Resources List, 1999-02 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Children's Storybook: Nutrition Education Resources (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Section B: DNS Published Resources for Youth
  - In-touch Science: Foods And Fiber By Patricia Thonney, Tracy Farrell and Charlotte Coffman (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - In The Bag! Families Sharing Science Together By Tracy Farrell and Patricia Thonney (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Two-part: Leader's Guide and Activities Sample Activity - Explore Seeds
  - The Humble Potato: Underground Gold By Marcia Eames-Sheavly and Tracy Farrell, Also see The Great American Peanut By Marcia Eames-Sheavly (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - A Pyramid of Snacks By Patricia Thonney (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Two Part: Teaching Guide and Video
  - Section C: Organizational Changes
  - Personnel (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - DNS Extension Faculty: Time % Responsibilities, 1998
    - Hazel E.Reed Human ecology Extension Professorship in Family Policy, 1999
  - Youth Priorities (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - State 4-H Office Future Newsletter: Four Priority Planning Areas, Spring 1999
    - Revisions for 1999 State Fair Book, 1999
  - Section D: Related DNS Extension Program Activities
  - Sisters Health Program, Carol Devine and Tracy Farrell (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - EFNEP 30 Year Celebration (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Section E: Newsletters
  - DNS Alert Newsletters (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Excerpts on Youth Programming and Resources
    - DNS Alert Index, 1997-1998
  - DNS Nutrition Newsletters, 1993-06, 1996-06 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Human Ecology News (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - 65th Anniversary Institute, 1991-01
    - Dean Firebaugh's Retirement, 1991-05
  - Box 10: News Notes, Food Services Management., DNS Alert, Perspectives 1955-1986
  - Inventory of Newsletters and Professional Perspectives (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Overview: Special Communication to agents had different titles:
      - Newsletters
        - News Notes Dept. of Food and Nutrition, 1950
        - News and Views Dept. of Food and Nutrition And Dept. of Human Nutrition and Food, 1969
        - Nutrition Alert Dept. of Human Nutrition and Food, 1975
        - DNS Alert Div. of Nutritional Sciences, 1975
      - Special mailings often in pouch with newsletter
        - Current legislation and regulatory events - either Food or Nutrition or both
        - Professional Perspectives - Background Information in depth for agent and professional use
      - Newsletter for nursing homes, small hospitals and resident care facilities
        - Highlights on Food Service Management
      - Pouch mailings also included FDA and commercial items if complimentary to current topics of concern as well as occasional Division newsletters
  - Section A: News Notes
  - Series, 1955-12-1959 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Series, 1960-1961 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Series, 1962-1963 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Section B: Highlights on Food Service Management
  - Series, 1967-1969 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Series, 1970-1972 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Series, 1973-1978 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Section C: News and Views (In Another Box)
  - Section D: Nutrition Alert
  - Prelude to dept. merging with School of Nutrition and becoming Division of Nutritional Sciences and changing title to DNS Alert, 1975-02-1975-05 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Section E: DNS Alert as sent to agents
  - Series, 1975-10-1979-12 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Series, 1980-02-1980-12 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Series except September issue, 1981-02-1981-12 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Series, 1982-01-1982-12 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Series, 1983-01-1983-12 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Section F: Professional Perspectives
  - Series, 1976-1980 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Series, 1981-1986 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Series (no. 3-6), 1987 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Series (no. 1 and 4), 1988 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Box 11: DNS Alert Newsletters, 1984-1990
  - Inventory of DNS Alert Newsletters, DNS Alert Newsletters sent to Extension agents statewide during the following periods:, 1984-1990 (11, Folder 1)
  - Series, 1984-01-1985-02 (11, Folder 2)
  - Series, 1985-03-1985-12 (11, Folder 3)
  - Series, 1986-01-1986-12 (11, Folder 4)
  - Series, 1987-01-1987-12 (11, Folder 5)
  - Series, 1988-01-1988-12 (11, Folder 6)
  - Two Issues, 1989-03-1989-04 (11, Folder 7)
  - Series with exception of September, 1990-04-1990-12 (11, Folder 7)
  - Box 12: DNS Alert Newsletters, 1993-1995
  - DNA Alert Newsletters, 1993-1995